<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief relation of the beginning and ending of the troubles of the Barbados, with the true causes thereof. / Set forth by A.B. a diligent observor of the times.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E708_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866201</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166640</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76756)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 109:E708[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief relation of the beginning and ending of the troubles of the Barbados, with the true causes thereof. / Set forth by A.B. a diligent observor of the times.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Cole in Leaden-Hall, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Printing-Press in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Barbados --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Barbados --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166640:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief RELATION OF THE BEGINNING and ENDING OF THE TROUBLES OF THE BARBADOS, With the true <hi>Cauſes</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set forth by</hi> A. B. <hi>a diligent Obſerver of the Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Peter Cole</hi> in <hi>Leaden-Hall,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop at the ſign of the <hi>Printing-Preſs</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal Exchange. 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:166640:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166640:2"/>
            <head>A Brief Relation of the Beginning and Ending of the Troubles of the <hi>Barbados,</hi> with the true Cauſes thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hileſt the Bloody Contention for the Peoples Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was in its height among the <hi>Engliſh Nation,</hi> The Iſland of <hi>Barbados</hi> (by the Opinion of its Governor Concurring happily with the quiet Enclination of of the People) was bound up with Principles of Neutrality, it being a Place which could not ad any Aſſiſtance to either of the contending Parties in <hi>England,</hi> and as newly Setled ſtood in neceſſity of Supplies from both, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like ſubtil States-men they temporized with al new Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, came they either from the Parliament or late King, holding firm their Reſolutions, until (the Parliament prevailing) multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the Royal Party being made Priſoners, were ſent thither to be ſold as Servants, and many Officers of that ſide to mend their Fortunes, applyed themſelves to that Place, and in ſuch conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Numbers, That by the Civility of the firſt Setlers, they got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Principal Offices of that Government, and by degrees drew the People, if not abſolutly to decline their former Peaceable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, yet in a great meaſure, to incline to the loſt Cavalier Party, by making the Current of all Preferments and Authority to Stream to thoſe that way affected: Among others of that Party who came thither, were two Brothers, Perſons of good eſteem once in their own Country; the elder, Colonel <hi>Humphry Walrond,</hi> bred a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166640:3"/>
Gentleman about <hi>London;</hi> the other, <hi>Edward Walrond,</hi> a Lawyer of the Temple, who finding the advantage of their parts, of the ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the People to receive any impreſſion, and the plain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penneſs of the then Governor, little doubted but in a ſhort time to gain the Government into their hands, and by that means amply to Repair their broken Fortunes out of the Eſtates of thoſe Perſons that had ſo freely ſupplyed their wants; Having therfore fixed an opinion in the good old Governor of their very honeſt meaning, as alſo in his Lady, in whom by reaſon of her quick and induſtrious Spirit, lay a great ſtroak of the Government: Their firſt ſtep was to drive Col. <hi>Guy Moleſworth</hi> out of the Iſland, who having been more Eminent in their Kings Service, the Brothers doubted would over-top them, when the Royal Party ſhould Declare, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cunningly Complained againſt him as a violent Cavalier, and one that ſaid, <hi>It would never be well in this Iſland, until the Round-heads Eſtates were given to the poor Cavaliers:</hi> This ſetled the better opinion of them, and gave them means in a ſhort time after to banniſh him the Iſland upon ſome advantages, which they took againſt him: This act ſo plauſibly performed, gave them encouragment to move further, and procure the Office of Treaſurer and Maſter of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines, and Capt. of the Platforms, to be put into the hands of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jant Major <hi>William Byam,</hi> a Souldier of Fortune, and one very fit for their turns; theſe things being fitted to their minds, they waited for an handſome occaſion to get to the height of their Ambition, which ſoon after thus preſented: The Inhabitants of the <hi>Barmudas</hi> having turned the well-affected to the PARLIAMENT off their Iſland, ſent an Agent to <hi>Barbados,</hi> requeſting them to make a League Defenſive and Offenſive, and to furniſh them with Arms and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition to Defend that Cauſe they had Declared for; which (though the two Brothers were earneſt to have granted) was by the great oppoſition of Col. <hi>James Drax</hi> denied, and only this gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>That for his Money he might buy what Ammunition he could get:</hi> This not taking, the yonger Brother did in the Name of the Governor Summon divers Gentlemen to meet, and there told them, That out
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166640:3"/>
of the good opinion the Governor had of them, they were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Committee to Conſider of the Safety of the Iſland, which was now near a great deal of Hazard if not prevented, alleadging in a very long, ſet, &amp; induſtriouſly, &amp; well penned Speech, That there was a very formidable Malignant party in the Iſland which daily encreaſed, and would in time maſter this Iſland, and turn all well-affected to the King from thence, and there was but Two wayes to prevent this ſuppoſed Danger: The firſt was, Extirpation of them; the ſecond, Toleration. For the firſt he and the major part voted, and then theſe Votes were carried to the Governor, but not made known to him, until an Oath of Secrecy was taken by him as was formerly taken by the Committee: Then an Aſſembly was called, where likewiſe after an oath of Secrecy by all preſent was ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken theſe Rotes were publiſhed, and after ſome Debates con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and a Committee appointed to Conſider of the quieteſt and moſt peaceable wayes of ſending theſe Malignants into Exile. But before that was concluded on, Col. <hi>Modyford</hi> drew up a Bill for the way of Toleration, and at the return of the Committee preſented the ſame, backed with ſo many Reaſons in order to the peace and plenty of this place, that they all unanimouſly were ſo apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of it as they quite retracted their firſt Votes, and agreed to the latter way, at w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> every man ſeemed well contented; but the Two Brothers, the yonger wherof having a ready wit, <hi>added ſuch a miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious oath to that law, &amp; ſuch ſevere cautions &amp; clauſes againſt non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts &amp; private conventicles,</hi> that this law ſo accompanied much diſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the well-affected to the Parliament, which was no leſs then the Brothers both expected and deſired: Before the publiſhing of this Law, Col. <hi>Drax</hi> and others, incited the honeſt Planters to Petition againſt it, and by ſtrong Reaſons given the Governor, prevailed with him not to publiſh it until their Petition were Anſwered. At the next Councel the Petitioners came, and the Governor now wel informed, declared for them; at which the <hi>Walronds</hi> in a rage roſe up and divers of the Councel with them, and diſſerted the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, leaving only two to ſit with him, at which time he ſtopped the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166640:4"/>
further proceeding of that Act, and diſmiſſed the Petitioners; from thenceforth the Brothers openly Declared the Governor to be a Roundhead, cunningly make Libels againſt themſelves and other eminent Perſons to draw them into diſcontent, and publiſh the ſame, as made by their then declared Enemies, and to make them beleeve they were Perſons in hatred equal with themſelves, and ſo in fine by ſuch Devices and Arts increaſed their party, and on <hi>May</hi>-eve, 1650. perſwaded a plain, but over credulous Gent. Col. <hi>Shelly,</hi> to beleeve, That the Independants (for ſo they were now ſtiled) had a Plot to ſeize the Magazine, and put all that loved the King to the Sword: The ſame Jealouſies they infuſed into the thoughts of Col. <hi>Read,</hi> who accompanied with <hi>Shelly</hi> and their Regiments, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced againſt the old Governor at the Bridge, who ſuddenly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened by an Alarum, had then by chance got Force enough to take the elder <hi>Walrond</hi> and <hi>Byam</hi> Priſoners; but ſo inconſiderable were the Governors Forces, and ſo weak his Counſels, that he was forced to ſend the ſaid <hi>Walrond</hi> to <hi>Shelly</hi> for a Parley, which was ſoon granted, and the next day plauſible Articles drawn up, ſuch as the elder <hi>Walrond</hi> pleaſed, and ſuch as he thought would beſt cloak his deſign from <hi>Shelly, Read,</hi> and other his abuſed Accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: But the poor old Governor now (though too late) ſaw throw the inſide of his miſchievous intentions, and therfore Commanded Col. <hi>Modyford</hi> (whom he had formerly forbidden) to Raiſe the Windward Regiment for his Reſtauration to that Authority which he was ſo eaſily fool'd out of; who immediatly iſſued his Orders to Leivt. Col. <hi>Burch</hi> for that purpoſe, which was by his activity ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in one night, ſo that Lievt. Col. <hi>Burch</hi> was upon his March with fifteen hundred Foot, and one hundred and twenty Horſe, and became very terrible to the <hi>Walronds,</hi> and would undoubtedly have turned the Scale, had not the elder <hi>Walrond</hi> by commanding tears to wait upon his deceitful profeſſions of Zeal, Faith, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty to the Governor, prevailed with him to ſend a Warrant to Command Lievt. Col. <hi>Burch</hi> to Diſband his Forces, and forthwith to repair to the Governor to attend his further pleaſure: This point
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166640:4"/>
ſo eaſily gained, made all men afraid to Act for the Governor, that would upon the perſwaſions of his Enemies be induced to Diſarm himſelf and his freinds, and made the <hi>Walronds</hi> look on themſelves as abſolute Princes, taking upon them in a very Kingly way, To give Orders, raiſe Horſe, grant Commiſſions, and like Princes indeed, To forget the Articles made, keeping only ſuch as were for their advantage; impudently alleadging, That no other Promiſes ought to be kept, by Perſons in their Condition. Whileſt all men began now to yeeld them a true or feigned Obedience, the Lord <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> who had been ſome while in the Road, gives notice to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of it, and that he had Authority from the King and the Earl of Carliſle to be Governor, and according to his Commiſſion deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be received: This new Pageant gave a mortal wound to the ill-got Principallity of the Brothers; for this man they could not Oppoſe without going againſt their declared Principles of Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their Kingly ſtalking-horſe; And yet they were ſo impudent as firſt privately with particular men they endeavoured to raiſe a Diſlike of him, ſaying, <hi>That he was once a Roundhead, and might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and that as things ſtood, it was eaſie to obtain any thing from the King:</hi> And after did in publick oppoſe his Reception; and truly their former influence, coupled with their preſent induſtry, prevailed ſo far, as though not to Refuſe, yet to ſuſpend his Lordſhips Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for three Months, in which time they made no doubt, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gain him to their devotion, or ſend him to <hi>Antigoa;</hi> during this time, They Proclaimed their King, forced the innocent Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents from their Eſtates and Families, ſet heavy Fines upon them, and after made themſelves a Committee for Sequeſtrations of all they had, and then tryed the Affections of every man, how they ſtood either to Them, or the Lord <hi>Willoughby:</hi> To ſome <hi>that were poor and Covetous,</hi> they promiſed ſhares of the Roundheads Eſtates: To others <hi>that were blindfold Cavaliers,</hi> they preſſed the danger of <hi>Willoughby:</hi> To others <hi>who moſt regarded their Liberty,</hi> they preſt the ſetting up of a Popular Government, which they did not ſtick to ſay <hi>was their intentions from the beginning, and that they loved it above all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166640:5"/>
other Formes</hi> In fine, to compaſs their ill begun deſigns, they obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved every mans Affections, and applyed themſelves to entertain them accordingly. Theſe practices were as well obſerved as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> who was now to Countermine or be loſt, and ſaw plainly he muſt be enforced to juggle as his Enemies did, and therefore to the Cavalier he was all King; and to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate party, he profeſſed a Diſlike of the preſent Proceedings; and finding them the greateſt Enemies <hi>Walrond</hi> had, he made no ſcrupl privatly to unfold himſelf to one of the eminenteſt of them, therefore ſending for Col. <hi>Modyford,</hi> he aſſured him, That all his Counſels ſhould be imployed in Compoſing the preſent Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here, and preventing the future Differences which may happen betwixt <hi>England</hi> and this Place, for which purpoſe Capt. <hi>George Martin</hi> was ſent into <hi>England</hi> with Inſtructions to gain him a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Parliament, which he averred above all things to deſire. The Moderate party verily beleeving his heart and words to agree, gave him Courage to take from the elder <hi>Walrond</hi> his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, and from both of them all Power and Authority in this Iſland, cauſed the Acts of Sequeſtrations to be Repealed, and an Act of Indemnity to be made, beſtowed many marks of Favor up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former Sufferers, and their remaining Families, in ſo much, That all men generally looked on him as a bleſſing ſent from God to preſerve them againſt the Tyranny of the two Brothers. About this time Col. <hi>John Colliton</hi> came to this Iſland, to whom likewiſe his Lordſhip unfolded his thoughts, and deſired him to Write to the Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> to procure a Commiſſion from the State of <hi>England</hi> for him, and did aſſure both him, Col. <hi>Modyford,</hi> and Col. <hi>Burch</hi> of his conſtant Reſolutions to perſevere in Moderating and Compoſing all things, and wiſhed them to aſſure all well-affected Perſons of it. This honeſt clearneſs in all his Actions laſted until <hi>March,</hi> 1651. when a Paſſenger from <hi>England</hi> brought him Letters of the great ſtrength the King of <hi>Scots</hi> had, and of the violent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of ſome of the Planters againſt him, that <hi>Martin</hi> was like to be Hanged for ſpeaking for him; and in fine, That the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166640:5"/>
were to expect nothing but Fire and Sword, no Terms to be granted, and the great preparations of Force to ſubdue this place: Then, and not till then, he began to change his Game, and openly profeſſed Defiance, and every day carreſſed and aſſured himſelf more and more of the violent Party, and yet cunningly promiſed the Moderate, <hi>That if ever good terms were offered, he would accept of them:</hi> This made moſt men joyn cheerfully in the putting the Iſland in a Poſture of Defence; the moſt Moderate, like true <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to ſell themſelves at a dear Rate, by chuſing to die, rather then to live leſs Free then any of their Country-men: Suddenly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> growing ſtill ſurer of the violent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, cauſed new Sequeſtrations to be laid on the baniſhed mens E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, killed and deſtroyed their Cattel and Stock, and did what miſchief he could unto them all without diſtinction. At length the Fleet arriving, after Summons, and Refuſal had paſt, Leivt. Col. <hi>Allen,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Francis Raynes,</hi> applyed themſelves by Letter to Col. <hi>Modyford,</hi> therein tendring all things of Fairneſs and Civility; which the ſaid Col. received with much contentment &amp; ſhewed the ſame to the Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> preſſing his Promiſe of Compoſure upon fair terms, which he not being able to deny, gave him Power by Letter to Treat, to know the Admirals Power, and next the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Articles he would inſiſt on: All which by a private Treaty being perfected, and Articles agreed on, to the Contentment of Col. <hi>Modyford,</hi> and Lievt. Col. <hi>Burch,</hi> to whom he from time to time communicated his Proceedings, with which his Lordſhip being made fully acquainted, and finding now no poſſibility of longer Diſſembling, plainly forſook all his old Promiſes, being encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the weakneſs of the Fleet, and the aſſurance of the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Party now truly loving him whom they found ſo much of their own Diſpoſition, and perfectly hating the <hi>Walronds</hi> for ever having doubted ſo true a Cavalier. In the mean time the admirable tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Sir <hi>George Ayſcue</hi> the States General ſhewed in the mannagement of theſe Affairs, cannot without breach of the laws of Hiſtory be omitted, for he diſcreetly weighing how little he was able to do
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166640:6"/>
by the Sword, being not provided with any conſiderable Land-Forces, the Enemy having at leaſt five thouſand Foot, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe at ſeveral Poſts quartered on the Sea-ſide, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring they were <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> found his beſt Weapon to be gentle and fair means, which he ſo ingeniouſly made uſe of, that though none durſt ſpeak well of him, yet moſt knowing Perſons were well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in their minds, that there could not be any danger in a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to thoſe that ſent him; And knowing it a dull thing to be all Courteſie, for to keep up the ſpirits of his own men, and give the Iſlanders a taſt what they could do, he beat up a Quarter at the <hi>Hole,</hi> and by the help of the <hi>Scots</hi> which came in the <hi>Virginia-fleet,</hi> another at <hi>Spikes Bay,</hi> both which were done in the night, and in both theſe was wonderous Succesful, and not having Power enough to proſecute theſe ſucceſſes, retired his Forces to his Ships, not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any further harm, which he might have done by firing Houſes, &amp;c. The Priſoners he took he uſed extreamly well, which ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed the good Opinion the People had of him, and forwarded his Deſigns more then ſome violent Perſons about him could have imagined. The Moderate Party were now to ſeek what to do, and yet their ends being honeſt, they were bold by Leivt. Col. <hi>Burch</hi> to move a Treaty in the Publick Aſſembly, ſeconded by Col. <hi>Hawly,</hi> and <hi>Modyford,</hi> and brought it ſo far that a Committee was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to draw Articles, which they did to the liking of moſt at the firſt reading, but being put off to the next day, the Lord <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> by himſelf and Inſtruments, had ſo dealt with the ſeveral Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that they Voted ſuch Articles to be ſent, as ſignified nothing but a Defiance: After this, followed Healths to the Deſtruction of them that would have Peace; Threats to all Moderate men; the Drunkards quibbingly alleadging. That all the Deſirers of Treaty were Traytors: And then began the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> to be odious to all moderate and good Men; which being well obſerved by Col. <hi>Modyford,</hi> he thinking himſelf not further obliged to ſolicite ſo obſtinate a man for his own good, or longer to continue under his Command, that had broke all Faith, &amp; thoſe Promiſes, for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:166640:6"/>
only he firſt undertook to adhere to him; privatly adviſing with Col. <hi>Colliton,</hi> and calling Col. <hi>Burch</hi> then his Leivt. Col. Capt. <hi>Hooper,</hi> and other Officers to him, they Reſolved to make the Lord <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> by Force to perform, what by honeſt perſwaſions could not be obtained. And therefore having over-night had Conference with Capt. <hi>Pack,</hi> Col. <hi>Drax,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Raynes</hi> on ſhore, who having Power from the General, gave him all the ſatisfaction that reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably he could deſire: On Saturday the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>January,</hi> Colonel <hi>Modyford</hi> drew his Regiment together, conſiſting of a thouſand Muſketiers, and one hundred and twenty Horſe, and in a ſhort Speech made them ſo ſenſible of the preſent Diſtractions of the Country, of the likelyhood of their Continuance, the violence of ſome men even in Councel and the Aſſembly, whereby the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Votes and Debates were loſt, the preſent wants of the Country, the willingneſs and abilities of thoſe Ships that lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them to give all poſſible Supply unto them, and finally the Articles which they offered, that they all Declared, That they would live and die with their Colonel in obtaining Peace upon thoſe Articles: Notice hereof being given a-Board, a Letter with the Articles encloſed was preſently diſdatched to the Lord <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby,</hi> perſwading him yet to ſhew himſelf ſo much an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and a Chriſtian as by an happy Accord to ſhorten the miſeries of this Iſland: but he was deaf, and that night beat up an out-Quarter of Horſe: in the mean time Col. <hi>Modyfords</hi> houſe about ſeven miles in the Country was (by his order) made a Garriſon for the State; the Priſoners at Capt. <hi>Middletons</hi> by them releived. On Munday the <hi>Rainbow</hi> came up, and Sir <hi>George</hi> came on Shore, had his Commiſſion publiſhed, and at the ſame time the Lord <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> was drawn down with about three thouſand men, but could neither hinder the Proclaiming the States Intereſt, or diſturbe the Peace-makers quarters, but that ſame night at midnight made a ſilent and ſhameful Retreat: Tueſday, Wedneſday, and Thurſday were ſo wet, that the Peace-makers could not advance againſt him; but the Friday being drawn out, and ready to March, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166640:7"/>
Lord <hi>Willoughbies</hi> Trumpet with a Letter earneſtly deſiring Peace, ſtopt further Proceedings; On which Treaty the Iſland was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the State, and the People aſſured their full Freedom and Liberties, which they now happily enjoy. Thus may you ſee that by the excellency of one mans temper and Conduct, with Gods bleſſings thereon, this rich ſpot of Land, containing at leaſt thirty thouſand Souls, Reduced and United to their Native Country without Bloodſhed, or any conſiderable expence of Treaſure. Their wiſe General well knowing that there could not be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Service to the State, then to preſerve his Conqueſts entire and without leſning, eſpecially when they are to be made on his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Country-men, which Succesful Rule of ſweetneſs he practiſed while he remained Governor here, whereby he hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely confirmed every Soule here to be faithful to the preſent flouriſhing Government of our Nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
